Finding aid to the Ada Louise Comstock Papers CA.MS.00015
Smith College Archives
Ada Louise Comstock Papers
1897-1998
Smith College Archives
Comstock, Ada Louise.
CA.MS.00015
3.125 linear feet (8 containers)
Acting President of Smith College, Dean of the College of Smith College, Professor of English at Smith College, and President of Radcliffe College. Contains biographical material, correspondence, materials related to professional and volunteer work, and photographs.
Biographical / Historical
Born on December 11, 1876 in Moorhead, Minnesota, Ada Comstock was the eldest of three children; she was bright, vivacious, and very much a tomboy in her early childhood. Her father, a successful lawyer, recognized her capabilities and potential and set about to cultivate them by encouraging an early and sound education for his daughter.
Ada completed her high school education at the age of fifteen and then went on to college. In 1895 she transferred from the University of Minnesota to Smith College, where she completed her last two years of undergraduate study. As a Smith student, Ada often questioned the established rules and norms of college life. While a resident of Hubbard House, she was given a case of champagne which the housemother felt should be given away. Instead, in what was characteristically her spirit, she decided to store it in the water cooler to refresh her friends!
After graduating from Smith in 1897, Ada went on to a graduate program at Moorhead State Normal School where she became certified to teach. She then entered Columbia University for graduate work in English, History, and Education, and by 1899 was ready to return home to look for a job. In 1907, after teaching rhetoric at the University of Minnesota, she was appointed the University's first Dean of Women. In this capacity, she was instrumental in improving the quality of life for the women of the college, arguing persistently that a college was responsible for one's physical and intellectual well-being.
In 1912, Ada came to Smith as the first ever Dean of the College and to teach English. Particularly challenging to her was the opportunity to advise and teach young women in an all-female institution. One of the most important tenets of her educational philosophy was the inculcation in young women of self-respect, one aspect of which was knowing how to employ oneself. Ada believed very strongly throughout her entire life that a college education should inspire women to take a part in the shaping of the world.
In 1917, when the Presidency of Smith College became vacant, Ada was given the responsibility of its operation for approximately 6 months, but was neither given the title of acting President nor was she considered for the position. Despite Ada's significant and numerous contributions to the College, Smith was not ready for its first woman President.
Ada was an early member of the Association of Collegiate Alumnae, later called the American Association of University Women which she served as president. She was a founding member and one of the five American voting delegates to the first conference of the International Federation of University Women in London in 1920 and at the second in Paris in 1922. One of their objects was the forwarding of higher education for women in every country in the world. She was active in other areas in public life as well. In 1929 she was the only woman named by President Herbert Hoover to an eleven-person commission to study problems of law enforcement. She was a president of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, Vice Chairman of the American Council of Institute of Pacific Relations and served on the National Committee for Planned Parenthood.
The chance to become the President of a women's college presented itself to Ada in 1923 when Radcliffe offered her the position of their first full-time President. Throughout most of her administration, Ada Comstock struggled with trying to maintain a balance between Radcliffe's association with Harvard and its establishment as an independent women's college. Under President Comstock, Radcliffe was able to launch a nationwide admission program, improve student housing, construct new classroom buildings and expand the graduate program. In short, Radcliffe's permanence was assured. In 1943, Ada felt her work at Radcliffe was complete. She had brought the institution to distinction and maturity, and it was now time to move on.
Her honors were numerous, fourteen honorary degrees were conferred on her, including Smith's L. H. D. in 1922. Each of the three institutions she had served, the University of Minnesota and Smith and Radcliffe Colleges have residence halls named for her.
At the age of sixty-seven, she stepped down from the Presidency and shortly after announced her marriage to Wallace Notestein, Sterling Professor Emeritus of History at Yale University, a man she had known since her days at the University of Minnesota. Retirement for Ada was an extremely busy period in her life. She continued to be actively involved with the Board of Trustees of Smith College, worked on plans for the graduate center at Radcliffe, did extensive educational committee work, administered a two-career household, and traveled extensively with her husband. Mrs. Notestein died in December of 1973.
[Some of this information was taken from the Ada Comstock Scholars Program's History of Ada Comstock at http://www.smith.edu/ada/history.php]
Scope and Contents
The Ada Louise Comstock Papers contain biographical materials, correspondence, employment histories, speeches and writings, information on her voluntary services and photographs that span Comstock's life and career as Dean of Smith College, President of Radcliffe College and retirement.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into five series:
I. Biographical Materials
II. Correspondence
III. Employment
IV. Photographs
V. Speeches, Writings, and Publications
Related Material
Class of 1897 Records
Ada Louise Comstock Diaries and Papers, Schlesinger Library, Radcliffe Institute for Advanced Study
Conditions Governing Access
Materials in the Smith College Archives are open for use, with the following exceptions: "Office Files," files of records created for the use of the administrative unit that created them, are closed to research for a period of 10 years following their creation.
Board of Trustees' records are closed permanently.
In all cases, the College Archives will continue to provide public access to materials that were intended to be public at the time of their creation (press releases, publications, etc.)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Source unknown.
Comstock, Ada Louise.; Smith College--Faculty,; Smith College--Presidents.; Radcliffe College--Presidents.; Swan, Mabel Dick.; Greene, Helen French, 1868-; Peloubet, Harriet Louise.; Solomon, Barbara Miller.
- Series I: Biographical Materials
  Scope and Contents
  This section of the collection contains an index to the collection, awards and degrees, information on Ada's marriage, memorabilia and obituaries.
  - Collection Index (Box 719.2, Folder 1)
  - General, 1923 - 1998 (Box 719.2, Folder 2)
  - Memories, 1974 (Box 719.2, Folder 3)
  - Awards and Degrees, 1958 - 1966 (Box 719.2, Folder 4)
  - Marriage, 1943 - 1969 (Box 719.2, Folder 5)
  - Obituaries, 1973 - 74; n. d. (Box 719.2, Folder 6)
  - Comstock House, 1975 - 1986 (Box 719.2, Folder 7)
  - "From Western Prairies to Eastern Commons: A Life in Education, Ada Louise Comstock Notestein, 1876 - 1973" -- By Barbara Miller Solomon, 1993 (Box 719.2, Folder 8)
- Series II: Correspondence
  This section of the collection consists of correspondence, both professional and personal with several letters to and from Ada's closest friend, Mabel Dick Swan.
  - Smith College, 1945 - 1967 (Box 719.2, Folder 9)
  - Mabel Dick Swan, 1937 - 1962 (Box 719.2, Folder 10)
  - Mabel Dick Swan, 1963 - 1969; n. d. (Box 719.2, Folder 11)
  - Mabel Dick Swan, 1972 - 73; n. d. (Box 719.2, Folder 12)
  - General, 1912 - 1973 (Box 719.2, Folder 13)
  - Helen French Greene, 1917 - 1923 (Box 719.2, Folder 14)
  - Harriet Louise Peloubet, 1932 - 36 (Box 719.2, Folder 15)
  - Comstock Family, 1914 - 1920 (Box 719.2, Folder 16)
- Series III: Employment
  This section contains folders housing information pertaining to much of Ada's work, both professional and voluntary dating from 1912 to 1969.
  - University of Minnesota, n. d. (Box 719.2, Folder 17)
  - Smith College: Dean's Reports, 1912 - 1923 (Box 719.2, Folder 18)
  - Smith College, 1912 - 1923 (Box 719.2, Folder 19)
  - Smith College: Press Board, 1920 (Box 719.2, Folder 20)
  - Radcliffe College: Inauguration, 1923 (Box 719.2, Folder 21)
  - Radcliffe College, 1923 - 1943 (Box 719.2, Folder 22)
- Series IV: Photographs
  The collection contains five folders of photographs dated from 1897 through 1967 with a few undated photos.
  - Photographs (Given to Walter F. Ellis), n. d. (Box 720, Folder 1)
  - General, 1897; n. d. (Box 720, Folder 2)
  - General, 1920; 1940 (Box 720, Folder 3)
  - As Mrs. Notestein, 1949 - 1967 (Box 720, Folder 4)
  - of portrait presented to Smith College by Cecilia Beaux, 1923 (Box 720, Folder 5)
- Series V: Speeches, Writings, and Publications
  This section of the collections is further divided into three smaller sections - speeches, writings and publications including two large bound collections of speeches and writings.
  - Publications, 1915 - 1945 (Box 720, Folder 6)
  - Reunions
    - Invitations from classes for reunions, 1947 - 1976 (Box 720, Folder 7)
    - Smith College Alumnae Council, 1946 (Box 720, Folder 8)
  - Speeches
    - Smith College A. A. U. W., 1922; n. d. (Box 720, Folder 9)
    - Smith College A. C. A., 1916; n. d. (Box 720, Folder 10)
    - Amherst College, 1921 - 22 (Box 720, Folder 11)
    - Bryn Mawr College, 1922 (Box 720, Folder 12)
    - "The College Curriculum as a Matter of Teaching", n. d. (Box 720, Folder 13)
    - Smith College Commencement, 1925 (Box 720, Folder 14)
    - Commencement Address, n. d. (Box 720, Folder 15)
    - "How to Become a Dean of Women", n. d. (Box 720, Folder 16)
    - Smith College
      - Greetings to the Class of 1921, 1917 (Box 720, Folder 17)
      - Heads of House, 1913 - 1921 (Box 720, Folder 18)
      - Higher Education, 1925; n. d. (Box 720, Folder 19)
      - League of Women Voters, n. d. (Box 720, Folder 20)
      - "Welcome to Madame Curie", 1921 (Box 720, Folder 21)
      - Phi Beta Kappa Society, n. d. (Box 720, Folder 22)
      - S. C. A. C. W., 1921; 1922 (Box 720, Folder 23)
      - Student Government, 1921 (Box 720, Folder 24)
      - "Prayer for Colleges", n. d. (Box 720, Folder 25)
      - "Vocational Training for Women", 1915 (Box 720, Folder 26)
      - on War Activities, n. d. (Box 720, Folder 27)
      - General, n. d. (Box 720, Folder 28)
      - Smith Clubs, 1912 - 1939 (Box 720, Folder 29)
    - General, n. d. (Box 721, Folder 1)
    - General, 1930s (Box 721, Folder 2)
    - General, 1940s (Box 721, Folder 3)
    - General, 1950s (Box 721, Folder 4)
    - on Press Release, 1949 (Box 721, Folder 5)
    - on Memorial Service for Elizabeth Cutter Morrow, 1955 (Box 721, Folder 6)
    - General (boxed), 1937 - 1940 (Box 721, Folder 7)
    - General: Compiled by Robert Loeffler, n. d. (Box 721, Folder 8)
  - Bound Collection of Speeches and Writings I, 1981 (Box 722)
  - Bound Collection of Speeches and Writings II, 1981 (Box 723)
  - Voluntary Services
    - Alumnae Association Class of 1897, 1947 - 1967 (Box 724, Folder 1)
    - President Mendenhall Inauguration, 1959 - 1969 (Box 724, Folder 2)
    - Smith College Panel on Postwar Planning, 1945 - 46 (Box 724, Folder 3)
    - Board of Trustees, 1940 - 44 (Box 724, Folder 4)
    - Board of Trustees, 1945 - 46 (Box 724, Folder 5)
    - Board of Trustees: Committee on Needs, 1945 - 46 (Box 724, Folder 6)
    - Board of Trustees: Committee on Needs (library), 1945 (Box 724, Folder 7)
    - Board of Trustees, 1946 - 47 (Box 724, Folder 8)
    - China Colleges - Commission on Women's Higher Education in China, 1945 - 46 (Box 724, Folder 9)
    - China Colleges - China Institute, 1945 - 47 (Box 724, Folder 10)
    - China Colleges - International Federation of University Women, n. d. (Box 724, Folder 11)
    - Reid Hall, 1947 - 1949 (Box 725, Folder 1)
    - Reid Hall, 1950 - 1954 (Box 725, Folder 2)
    - Reid Hall, 1955 - 1958 (Box 725, Folder 3)
    - Reid Hall, 1959 - 1960 (Box 725, Folder 4)
    - Reid Hall, 1961 - 1965 (Box 725, Folder 5)
  - Smith College Alumnae Council, 1937 - 1960 (Box 725, Folder 6)
    - Smith College Anniversary Observance Committee, 1948 - 49 (Box 725, Folder 7)
    - Smith College Anniversary Fund, 1945 - 46 (Box 725, Folder 8)
  - RESTRICTED
    - Trustees Committee of Instruction, 1945 - 49 (Box 725)
    - Correspondence re: Deanship, 1945 - 47 (Box 726, Folder 1)
    - Candidates for Dean (in alphabetical order), 1945 - 48 (Box 726, Folder 2)
    - Committee to find President, 1948 - 49 (Box 726, Folder 3)
    - Selection of New Trustee (1946), 1945 - 46 (Box 726, Folder 4)